Guide to the Records of the NYU Medical Center RG 13.1
New York University Archives
Records of the NYU Medical Center
1942-1979
RG 13.1
New York University Archives
6.0 linear feet
This collection contains minutes of the Board of Directors of the NYU Medical Center from 1942 to 1979.
New York University. Medical Center.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by date.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Minutes
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains minutes and supplemental materials of meetings of the NYU Medical Center Board.
History of the New York University Medical Center
The NYU Medical Center was established to expand NYU's overall program of medical education, research, and patient care. It combined the existing University and Bellevue Hospital Medical College with additional resources to meet its mission of educating physicians, conducting scientific research, and treating patients. In 1941, at the time of its 100th anniversary, a vision and a plan for the School of Medicine's development came from two young faculty members: Donal Sheehan, Professor of Anatomy and Acting Dean, and Howard C. Taylor, Jr., Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology. Their vision came together in a 1945 report to the University called "The Mission of a Medical School," which called for worthy and adequate buildings, a program of graduate education, expansion of the activities of the university, close proximity to Bellevue Hospital, flexibility and individuality in learning, and confidence in research. By 1947 a site for the new Medical Center had been chosen and the following details completed: the University was granted a charter to establish and operate a hospital and clinic; the University formally established the New York University-Bellevue Medical Center, with its own Board; the University acquired 11 acres of land between First Avenue and the East River Drive and from 30th to 34th streets, and engaged architects; and the City agreed to close streets in the area and transfer title to the University, for which the University agreed to exchange a parcel of land for construction of an Institute of Forensic Medicine. Also by 1947 $6.5 million had been raised. Units of the Medical Center then sprang up in the following order: Institute of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation (1951); Medical Science Building and the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Institute (1955); Hall of Residence and Alumni Hall (1957); and University Hospital (1963).
The Medical Center currently consists of two hospitals, Tisch Hospital and Rusk Institute of Rehabilitation Medicine, and the New York University School of Medicine.
Sources:
Medicine, School of -- History, Archives H, University Archives
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The collection was transferred to the University Archives from the Medical Center.
New York University.; Medical colleges.; Minutes.
- Series I: Minutes
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042267750
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226775 0
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Council Meeting, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of the Meetings of the Sub-Committees of the Council Committee on Medicine and Dentistry, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Planning Committee Minutes, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Medical Center Board of Trustees - Building Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226776 8
  - Medical Center Board of Trustees - Finance Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Medical Center Board of Trustees - Building Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center - Memorandum of Understanding with City of New York, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center - Supplemental Agreement between the City of New York and NYU for the exchange of Lands, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center Campaign - Site Development Plant, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center -Original Charter and Amendments, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center - Property, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Medical Center - Closing of Streets - Deed, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Medical Center - Property, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Medical Center - Closing of Four Streets, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Medical Center - Closing of Four Streets, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Medical Center - Transfer of Assets and Liabilities, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Medical Center - Photostats of Certificates, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees Minutes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Medical Center Meeting - Board of Trustees J, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Board of Trustees - Medical Center Minutes - August 3, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Board 0f Trustees - Medical Center October 11, 1948 meeting (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Medical Center - Board of Trustees, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Medical Center Sundry Meetings, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Medical Center, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226777 6
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Medical Center Board Minutes, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Minutes of Meetings, NYU Bellevue Medical Center, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226778 4
  - Minutes of Meetings, NYU Bellevue Medical Center, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Meetings, NYU Bellevue Medical Center, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center Minutes - Extra Sets, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Minutes of Meetings, NYU Bellevue Medical Center, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of Meetings, NYU Bellevue Medical Center, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center Minutes - Extra Sets, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226779 2
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226780 0
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center Minutes, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center Minutes, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)